<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="void.AT.lessvoid.DOT.com">void256</author>
    <title>Nifty Getting Started - Introduction</title>
  </properties>
  <meta name="keyword" content="nifty, nifty gui, introduction"/>
  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>This explains what you need to download and get you up and running with Nifty GUI.</p>
      <subsection name="What is Nifty and how does it work?">
        <p>With Nifty you're using xml-files to define your graphical user interface. This means you use
        xml to position elements on the screen. You can then add different effects to the elements.
        Effects can change the appearance of elements on screen. You can move elements in position for instance or alpha
        blend them in. There are also a lot of different hover-effects available that you can use to make interacting
        with the elements interessting.</p>
        <p>To add logic to your user interface you write simple java classes. More on that in the
        <a href="hello-world.html">Hello World Example</a>.</p>
        <p>Nifty was designed to be as easy as possible be included into existing lwjgl-applications. This basically
        means, that you initialize lwjgl the usual way and just call nifty when you need it. Nifty uses the current
        Displaymode and adapts to it.</p>
        <p>Again, more on that in the <a href="hello-world.html">Hello World Example</a>.</p>
      </subsection>  
      <subsection name="Ok, What do I need to download?">
        <p>Nifty is currently available in two different jar-files:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>A "complete" jar-file that combines all needed dependencies in one file. You probably want to
          download this version if you just want to try out nifty.</li>
          <li>A "stand alone" version. In this case you'll need additional dependencies in your classpath
          to successful get it running (Explained below).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>You can find both version at the
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=223898">sourceforge download page</a>.</p>  
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Nifty Dependencies">
        <p>Nifty uses <a href="http://www.lwjgl.com/">http://www.lwjgl.com/</a> as the OpenGL rendering backend as well as
        <a href="http://slick.cokeandcode.com/">Slick2D</a> as a supporting library. For parsing XML-Files it also uses
        <a href="http://www.extreme.indiana.edu/xgws/xsoap/xpp/">XPP3</a>.</p>
        <p>You can view the current dependencies on the <a href="../dependencies.html">Project Dependencies Page</a>.</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>